So we just got done adding numbers with
gates with carry. But now we're going to
do something a little more difficult, which
is storing data with gates. And so that basic
is a way we can create memory systems, whether
it's registers inside of the CPU or high-speed
memory. We can create ways to store zeros and
ones over time. The key there is over time.
So we'll it'll take us a while to develop this
concept but the key thing here is that we use
feedback loops and in this circuit which calls is
called a set reset latch it basically has this Q
output and a Q not output and you'll notice that
the there is a top NOR gate and a bottom NOR gate
and the top output is get put as one of the inputs
to the bottom norate and the bottom output is put
is one of the inputs to the top nor gate. Now
you'll look at the little SRQ truth table and
and what happens is if Q has a value and S and R
are zero, the value of Q will be maintained. So
let's just let's just trace that through. So let's
just assume that R and S are zero and Q is one.
So the the one from Q is the second input to the
lower N norgate and that is a one input. So the
output of this lower N norgate is a zero which is
then the input to the top NOR gate. And as soon
as the the the input the the the Q not input to
the top N norgate is zero and R is zero as well
then that means that Q is one because it's a NOR
gate and Q is one so it goes to the bottom but Q
Q being one and S being zero means that Q knot
is zero the zero goes back up R being zero and
a zero 0 equals 1. So what happens is once Q is
one, it stays one. It's sticky. Now you can put
in combinations of S and R to set the value
for Q. If you look at the truth table, if you
set S to zero and R to one, then the Q becomes
a zero. And then if you set the R back to zero,
it's Q stays zero. And if you set S to one and R
to zero, then Q becomes a one. But then if you set
that S back to zero, then Q maintains. So we can
store either a zero in the Q or a one in Q. And
then as long as we keep the inputs SNR0, that one
just goes round and round and round between those
two NOR gates. So we're going to cover this a
little bit more. Here's the truth table. Now,
we're just not going to show those NOR gates.
We're just going to call this an SR latch. Again,
that's what we do. We make take two gates and make
a component so we can talk about it. When SNR are
zero, the latch maintains its internal state. That
Q output of one says that means that we set it
to one at some previous time and now we're just
putting inputs of 0 0 and the output stays one.
So if we have S of one and R of zero then that
makes the internal storage to one and then what
you've got to do is you got to take that S down to
zero but then the output maintains. So two zeros
means keep your state. Now if we make the S be a
zero and the R be a one that's going to set the
output to zero. And then the next thing you do
is you set R to zero and then the output stays
Now, how we do this is a little bit tricky,
right? And we'll we'll make smarter latches,
but this is the simplest latch, and it's literally
two NOR gates. Okay, that's it. Now, we're going
to have to build some more logic because this is
kind of inconvenient because that 2-1 situation
is kind of a pain in the neck. Now, I'll just
let you know that you can try to build an SR
latch using two NOR gates in my simulator, and
it won't work. Now maybe someday I will make the
circuit emulation of my digital logic simulator
better. But the problem is is that because this
is a timebased circuit with feedback, you have to
build a circuit emulation that understands that
these two things are happening round and round
and round and round and and you can build them,
but it's a lot harder to build them because you
have to deal with time rather than just zeros and
ones flowing through a circuit. So, my circuit
emulator because I want to keep it simple and
easy to use, it really deals with what we call
combinatoric circuits, which kind of the ones
and the zeros move from one side to the other.
Um, but the feedback ones, I can't do it. So,
what you have to do in my circuit emulator is use
the SR component, which does work because it's not
really two norates. It's a little component that
the software understands. So don't yell at me and
don't f file a GitHub uh issue if you try to build
an SR latch and it doesn't work and that's under
under unfortunate. Okay, so I mentioned that
the SR latch is kind of uh clunky, right? The
SR latch is you're you're not allowed to give it
one one as input. Okay. And so the latch that is
more useful is what we call a gated D latch. And
the gated Dlatch has basically a clock input and
a data input. And the way it works is as long as
the clock is zero, Q stays the same thing, right?
So whatever it was before and as soon as clock is
set to one, that then copies D into the internal
state. So if you set clock to one and D to zero,
the internal state becomes zero. And if you set
clock equals 1 and D equals 1, then the internal
state is one. And then you set clock back back
to zero and that zero or one stays over time. If
you look at it, there's several ways to build it,
but in this case, I'm using two NAND gates with
the feedback loop. And then you're kind of there's
like an S and an R in the middle of it, but then
there's this this the D and the C are set up so
that it can never send the wrong value into the
the SR like latch. Right? So you have this bit of
logic in the beginning that says when C is one,
copy D into the latch part and when C is zero,
ignore what is happening on D. So that's another
way to look at this. If we start with one in in
in the state in the internal value and we have the
clock of zero and the D is zero that at this point
D is being ignored because the clock is zero. Then
what we want to do is we want to store a zero in
it. So we we pulse the clock to be one and that
at that moment copies the zero into the one bit
latch and then we can set the clock back to zero
and then the zero will be remembered. So we don't
really care what the DV value is once the clock
is back to zero. You can flip the DV value back
as much as you like when the clock is zero. So
you can set D to one. The clock is still zero
and the output is still zero. Then you pulse
the clock by setting it to one. And then the
one is copied into it and to the output. And then
when we're done copying, we set the clock back to
zero. And the D is one. But then you can set the
D to zero because as the while the clock is zero,
the D is being ignored. And so you can see how
this you put whatever value you want on the D
and then you pulse the clock to copy D into the
latch. That's why they called it a gated D latch.
The clock acts as the gate. When the clock is
high, it copies its input. When the clock is low,
it ignores its input. And we're going to do what
we always do, and that is combine these things,
3D latches, and we're going to make a threebit
register. And we're going to represent in this
three-bit register numbers from 0 through 7.
So, we have three bits, a ones bit, a two's bit,
and a four's bit. And we're going to we have a
switch that has ones, twos, and fours that's going
into the D of each of the corresponding ones. And
then we have a single clock pulse. We're going to
pulse them all at the same time. So the internal
storage of the bits is 101. And so we can take
the output of the three bits and feed it into a
Nixie tube and get it out. Once we can build this,
we don't need to make three one bit latches. We
can make a three-bit latch. And that's what we're
going to use going forward. And that's pretty much
what a register is inside of a microprocessor in
that it's a three-bit latch and somewhere
it's getting its operands, a ones column,
a tw's column, and a four's column. And then we
pulse the clock to copy from those inputs into
the register. So the register then the clock goes
back to zero. So the register stores a value for a
while until we hit the clock button and it copies
its inputs again. Then we take the clock back to
zero and then it stays the same. After a while,
we'll we'll use the convenient stuff. Now we
have registers and we have Nixie tubes and we can
copy the output of the register to the Nixie tube
and we can see what the value is inside of the
Nixie tube. And so you can see that we're slowly
but surely, you know, building all the stuff
that might eventually become a microprocessor,
right? You know, we're building logic, putting
them together. I don't know what this might be.
This might be a half adder for all I know from
an old 1970s computer. But slowly but surely we
are deciding what to put on our CPU traces which
is wires and gates transistors to do addition,
subtraction, jumping, the kinds of things that
computers want to do. [Music] [Applause] [Music]